{
  "reference_number": "2093",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "Short lived gases (Such as methane) a disproportionately large percentage of our emissions, so working to reduce them in addition\n\n to long lived gases will have the greatest potential benefits."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "NZ shouldn't feel like it has to piggy back off other countries. That option creates less of an incentive to make real changes. Also not\n too keen on relying too heavily on trees for carbon sequestration as this is, at most a temporary solution, and the future use of those\n trees also has to be considered in terms of their usefulness as a carbon sink."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Without short term steps, it is easy to loose track of the large, far away goal, so makes it more likely you will meet the big goal."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "Think that allowing some ability to review can be used to address changes in circumstance while retaining short term stability,\n although this would be at the cost of more potential for politically motivated alterations to budgets."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Can be useful to adapt to sudden change, but will require well defined limits in the legislation and amendments should not be able to\n\n be undertaken without consideration of how they might affect future budgets and the overall goal."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Agree with considerations on the basis that social effects are given a higher weighting than economic and fiscal effects (As in the\n\nnested egg model of sustainability compared to the triple bottom line model)."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Would things ever get done if there was no timeframes apart from this far off 2050 end goal?"
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Also agree that the commission should have some ability to hold government to account if goals and budgets aren't set or met and\n\nthat government should have to be able to justify when it deviates sharply from advice provided to it by the commission in their role\nas independent experts."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "Take this position with the proviso that government should have to be able to justify when it deviates sharply from advice provided to\nit by the commission in their role as independent experts."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "We are going to have to adapt to some extent. Adaptation is not often talked about until it's forced upon us and a measure of pre-\n\nplanning can be useful to at least make sure there are workable systems in place for when adaptation is forced, or allow for more\npreemptive adaptation."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Don't think that central government should have responsibility for the detailed adaptation planning for the whole country. Having a\n\nhierarchy guided by central government would be more useful by providing strong guidance while allowing for a measure of variation\nto suit local contexts and distributing some of the administrative load. Will be most successful if central government also provides a\nsupporting role empowering local government to effectively plan within the guidance, priorities etc. laid out by central government."
    }
  ]
}
